here's how to find the total number of
gifts in the 12 Days of Christmas using
a geometric argument on the first day of
Christmas you get one partridge in a
pear tree on the second day you get the
Partridge in the pear tree and the two
turtle doves on day three you get three
French hens and the gifts from day two
on day four you get four calling Birds
and the gifts from day three on day five
you get five golden rings and the gifts
from day four on day six you get six
geese and all the gifts from day five on
day seven you get seven swans and all
the gifts from day six on day eight you
get eight maids and all of the previous
gifts on day nine you get nine ladies
dancing in all the previous gifts on day
10 you get 10 Lords and all of the
previous gifts on day 11 you get 11
Pipers piping and all of the previous
gifts and finally on day 12 you get 12
drummers and the previous gifts so how
many total gifts have you obtained over
the 12 days to figure this out we employ
a trick we imagine three people getting
all of these gifts so that we actually
have three copies of the gifts we take
the gifts from the second person and
glue them together like this with the
gifts from the first person we then form
this stack finally we can use the stack
of gifts from the third person to lay
them down in order like this as we fill
in this diagram we see that the final
shape will be a perfect rectangle by
construction the length of this
rectangle is two more than the total
number of days so it's 12 + 2 which is
14 on the other hand the width of this
rectangle is equal to the total number
of new gifts each day so it's equal to
the sum of the first 12 positive
integers but this sum is the total
number of gifts obtained on day 12 which
is half of this 13x 12 rectangle
pictured here so the sum of the first 12
positive integers is 13 * 12 / 2
therefore this construction shows us
that 3 * the total number of gifts
received is equal to the area of this
rectangle which is 14 * 13 * 12 12 ID 2
but this means the total number of gifts
is 14 * 13 * 12 / 6 which is
364 in the song The 12 Days of Christmas
they've given 364
gifts